A Guide to the Zachariah Johnston Papers, 1742-1856
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Zachariah Johnston Papers, 1742-1856
Library of Virginia
23893
0.225 cubic feet, negative photostats.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Ann and Susan Johnston, Lexington, Virginia, through Howard M. Wilson, Fisherville, Virginia, 25 November 1952.
Biographical/Historical Information
Zachariah Johnston was born in 1742 in Augusta County, Virginia, to William Johnston and Ann Johnston. He attended Liberty Hall Academy and later was a trustee of Washington College. Johnston was a prosperous farmer by the time the American Revolution began. In 1776, he was appointed a captain in the county militia. Johnston's company actively patrolled against Indian uprisings, and, in 1781, participated in the Virginia campaign which led to Lord Cornwallis' surrender. Representing Augusta County in the House of Delegates from 1778 to 1791, Johnston was chair of the House committee on religion and helped pass the "act for establishing religious freedom" in 1786. After he moved to Rockbridge County, Virginia, in 1792, he represented that county in the House of Delegates in 1792 and 1797-1798. An opponent of paper money, and a proponent of court reform and payment of British debts, Johnston supported the federal Constitution in 1788. As Augusta County's representative to the ratifying convention, he was influential in having his section of the state unanimously vote for ratification. In the 1790s, Johnston was interested in connecting Virginia's western rivers to the Potomac River. Johnston owned three plantations in Rockbridge County, one in Augusta County, and lands in Kentucky. He married Ann Robertson (d. 1818), and they had eleven children. He died 7 January 1800 in Rockbridge County.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1742-1856 (bulk 1772-1800), of Zachariah Johnston (1742-1800) of Augusta and Rockbridge Counties, Virginia, consisting of: accounts, affidavits, agreements, appraisals, birth records, bonds, certificates, correspondence, deeds, genealogies, inscriptions, land grants, lists, notebooks, plats, poems, promissory notes, receipts, reports, and wills. The bulk of the collection is correspondence between Johnston, his sons, other family members, friends, and political colleagues; and deals with family business and news, land holdings in Virginia and Kentucky, and political matters. Also includes a biography of Johnston by Matthew White Paxton, Jr. (1898-1987).
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Related Material
Zachariah Johnston Correspondence, 1781-1797 (LVA accession 22031)
Contents List
- Cemetery inscription notes. Elizabeth Johnston died 11 April 1742 and John Johnston died 25 August 1756., 1 p. (1 print)
- Church letter. William Johnston and wife, Ann, certified as having lived for two years in the bounds of [Notingham?], 1 June 1747, 1 p. (1 print)
- Promissory note. William Wright, schoolmaster, to W[___] Johnston, 24 January 1749, 1 p. (1 print)
- Promissory note. Robert McCutchon to William Johnston, 27 March 1750, 1 p. (1 print)
- Deed. James McDowell to Joseph Lapesly, both parties of Augusta County, 400 acres in Augusta County, recorded Augusta County, 18 June 1752, 2 p. (2 prints), mutilated
- Receipt. Money received by Robert Warnock from James Phillips on account of Patrick Burns, 5 March 1756, 1 p. (1 print)
- Birth records of Johnston Family, 1763-1783, 1 p. (1 print)
- Bond. Zachariah Johnston and Thomas Calbreath to Robert and James Thompson, both parties of Augusta County, 16 September 1772, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Alexander Robertson, Castle [___], to Zachariah Johnston. Augusta [County], 9 August 1776, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Zachariah Johnston, Long Meadow [Augusta County], to [___], 30 January 1779, 1 p. (1 print)
- Receipt. Money received by James Frazer from Zachariah Johnston, 28 April 1779, 1 p. (1 print)
- Agreement. James Douglass, Kentucky County, with Zachariah Johnston, Augusta County, 9 September 1779, 1 p. (2 prints), copy
- Letter. Zachariah Johnston, Long Meadow, Augusta County, to [___], 3 and 6 January 1780, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Samuel Wright to [___], 10 January 1780, 1 p., (1 print)
- Letter. Samuel Wright to Zachariah Johnston, 12 January 1780, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. [Zachariah Johnston], Long Meadow, [Augusta County], to [Samuel? Wright], 14 January 1780, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Samuel Wright to Zachariah Johnston, 21 January 1780, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. James Douglas, Harrodsburg, to [___], 21 January 1780, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. James Douglas, Harrodsburg, to [___], 18 February 1780, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Zachariah Johnston, Richmond, to [Edmund Randolph], 22 March 1781. Included on reverse is Randolph's reply, 23 March 1781, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. James Douglas, Williamsburg, to [___], 1 January 1782, 1 p. (1 print)
- Receipt. Money received by James Waddell from Capt. Johnston, 4 November 1782, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Zachariah Johnston, Long Meadow, Augusta County, to [___] Dugles, Williamsburg, 9 January 1783, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Zachariah Johnston, Falls of Ohio, to Mrs. Ann Johnston, Augusta County, 11 May 1784, 2 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. [Zachariah Johnston], Long Meadow, [Augusta County], to [___], 21 September 1784, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Alexander Robertson, [Harl?]ins Spring, to [Zachariah Johnston], 8 December 1784, 1 p. (1 print)
- Receipt. Money received by W. Fitzhugh from Z. Johnston on account of Col. Alex. McClennehan for use of John Carter, 23 November 1785, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. George Clendinen, Greenbrier County to [___], 20 April 1786, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. [___], Harlings Springs, to Capt. Zachariah Johnston, Augusta County, 10 June 1786, 1 p. (1 print), incomplete
- Letter. Alexander Robertson, Mercer County, to Capt. Zachariah Johnston, Augusta County, 23 September 1787, 3 p. (4 prints)
- Letter, Zachariah Johnston, Richmond, to Mrs. Ann Johnston, Augusta County, 26 October 1787, 2 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. George Clendinen, Richmond, to [___], 7 December 1787, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Wills. Joseph Lapsley, Sr., recorded Rockbridge County, 4 April 1792, [2 p. (2 prints), copy]; and Joseph Lapsley, Jr., recorded Rockbridge County, 3 April 1792, [2 p. (2 prints), copy]
- Letter. John Harvie to Capt. Zachariah Johns[t]on, Augusta [County], 7 July 1788, 3 p. (4 prints)
- Bond. William Galloway, Botetourt County, to Zachariah Johnston, 18 September 1788, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. George Clendinen, Staunton, to [___], 10 January 1789, 2 p. (3 prints)
- Certification of election of Zachariah Johnston as elector to vote in the presidential election, Botetourt County and surrounding counties, 14 January 1789, 2 p. (2 prints), copy
- Letter. W. Crogham, Louisville, to [___], 24 August 1789, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. George Clendinen, Staunton, to [___], 23 August 1789, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. John Johnston, Botetourt, to father, [Zachariah Johnston], 20 October 1789, 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. G[eorge] Mason, Gunston Hall, to Zachariah Johnston, Richmond, 29 October 1789, 3 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. Ed[ward] Carrington, Charlottesville, to Zachariah Johnston, Augusta County, 22 April 1790, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Ed[ward] Carrington, Richmond, to Zachariah Johnston, Augusta [County], 30 April 1790, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston, Philadelphia, to father, Zachariah Johnston, Augusta [County], 4 May 1790, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston, Philadelphia, to father, Zachariah Johnston, Augusta County, 6 July 1790, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Zachariah Johnston to son, James Johnston, 2 August 1790, 4 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston, Philadelphia, to father, Zachariah Johnston, Augusta County, 20 September 1790, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Th[omas] Jefferson, Monticello, to Zachariah Johnson, (sic) 7 October 1790, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. G[eorge] Mason, Gunston Hall, to Zachariah Johnston, Richmond, 3 November 1790, 3 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. George Clendinen, Richmond, to [___], 7 December 1790, 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston, Philadelphia, to father, Zachariah Johnston, Augusta County, 8 January [17]91, 3 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. Zachariah Johnston, [Long] Meadow, [Augusta County], to Major Croghan, 2 February 1791, 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston, Philadelphia, to father, Zachariah Johnston, Augusta County, 1 March 1791, 3 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. Alexander Martin, Bourbon County, to [___], 1 April 1791, 1 p. (1 print), incomplete?
- Letter. George Craig to Zachariah Jonston (sic), 18 June [17]91, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston, Philadelphia, to mother, Mrs. Ann Johnston, 7 July [17]91, 3 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. J[ohn] Johnston, Philadelphia, to father, Zachariah Johnston, Augusta County, 14 September 1791, 3 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. William Shannon, Jefferson County, to Zachariah Johnston, Richmond, 20 September 1791, 3 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. James Coursey to [___], 12 November 1791, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. James Monroe, Philadelphia, to Zachariah Johnson (sic) Richmond, 14 November 1791, 2 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. G[eorge] Mason, Gunston Hall, to Zachariah Johnston, Richmond, 18 November 1791, 2 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. Arthur Campbell, Richmond, to Zachariah Johnstone (sic), Richmond, 21 November 1791, 2 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. A[ndre]w Moore, Philadelphia, to Zachariah Johnston, Richmond, 22 November 1791, 2 p. (4 prints)
- Receipt. Money received by John Logan from Zachariah Johnson (sic), to be delivered to James Davies of Lincoln County, 20 December 1791, 1 p. (1 print)
- Account. Zachariah Johnston with George Kirker, 1792, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Arthur Campbell, Washington, to [___], 5 January 1792, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Ed[ward] Carrington, Richmond, to Zachariah Johnston, 29 January 1792, 4 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. Ed[ward] Carrington, Richmond, to Zachariah Johnston, Providence Hill [Rockbridge? County], 27 March 1792, 2 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. Henry Lee, Richmond, to Zachariah Johnston, Rockbridge [County], 27 March 1792, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Henry Lee, Richmond, to Zachariah Johnston, Providence Hill, Rockbridge [County], 5 May [17]92, 2 p. (4 prints)
- Church letter. Capt. Z[achariah] Johnston and wife, Ann, and children, certified in good standing, 21 May 1792, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Henry Lee, Richmond, to [___], 26 June [17]92, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. [Aug]ustine Davis, Richmond, to Zachariah Johnston, 11 December 1792, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Baird, Greencroft, to Zachariah Johnston, Richmond, 14 December 1792, 2 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. W. Croghan, Louisville, to Zachariah Johnston, Augusta [County], 7 January 1793, 1 p. (2 prints), partly illegible
- Letter. Jacob Peck, Staunton, to [___], 21 February 1793, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Micheal (sic) Coger, Fayette County, Kentucky, to [___], 7 April 1793, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Robert Porterfield, So[uth] River, to Capt. [Zachariah] Johnston, 24 June 1793, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Adam Craig, Richmond, to [___], 12 December 1793, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Composition book of George Johnston, 1794, 14 p. (8 prints)
- Letter. John H. Reynolds to "Mr. Johnstone," 19 March 1794, 3 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. Adam Craig, Richmond, to [___], 21 March 1794, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. George Nicolson, Richmond, to [___], 10 June 1794, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston, Staunton, to father Zachariah Johnston, Rockbridge, 5 March [17]95, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Adam Craig, Richmond, to [___], 21 April 1795, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Notice. John Brown to Zachariah Johnston, 29 August 1795. Enclosed is oath form., 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Alexander Martin, Bourbon County, Kentucky, to [___], 1 December 1795, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. J. McCue, Long Meadow, [Augusta County], to Capt. Z[achariah] Johnston,5 January 1796, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. William McKee, Lincoln County, to Capt. Zachariah Johnston, Rockbridge, 6 August 1796, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston, Staunton, to father, Zachariah Johnston, Rockbridge, 8 August [17]96, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Daniel Tr[abue?], Woodford County, to Col. Zachariah Johnson (sic), 24 September 1796, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Daniel Trabue, Woodford County, to Col. Zachariah Johnson (sic), Rockbridge County, 24 September 1796, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Affidavits. Hugh Fitzpatrick, James Frazer, Isaac McClure, and John McClure testify as to the Revolutionary War service of Hugh Fitzpatrick, Augusta County, 3 November 1796, 3 p.
- Letter. Edm[und] Randolph, Richmond, to Zachariah Johnston, Rockbridge, 11 January 1797, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Edm[und] Randolph, Fredericksburg, to Zachariah Johnston, Staunton, 7 [May?] 1797, 1 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. Michael Coger, Fayette County, Kentucky, to [___], 5 July 1797, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. A[dam] Craig, Richmond, to [___], 14 July 1797, 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. James Robertson, to [___], 26 August 1797, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Robert Porterfield to Capt. [Zachariah] Johnston, 25 October 1797, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Alexander Henderson, Dumfries, to Zachariah Johnston, Richmond, 1 December 1797, 3 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. [Zach]ariah Johnston, Richmond, to [___], 14 December 1797, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. George Johnston, Rockbridge [County], to father, Capt. Zachariah Johnston, 20 December 1797, 1 p. (1 print)
- Will. Zachariah Johnston dated 9 January 179[8?], 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston to [___], 26 February [17]98, 1 p. (1 print), incomplete
- Letter. George Johnston, Montgomery, to father, [Zachariah Johnston], 4 June 1798, 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. George Johnston, Montgomery, to brother, [___], 9 June [17]98, 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. George Johnston, Montgomery, to father, [Zachariah Johnston], 4 September [17]98, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. William McKee, Lincoln County, to Capt. Zachariah Johnston, 24 October 1798, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. William McKee, Lincoln County, to Capt. Zachariah Johnston, 27 November 1798, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. John Mines, Charlestown, Berkeley County, to Zachariah Johnston, Lexington, Rockbridge County, 22 December 1798, 2 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Thomas Johnston to brother, [A. Johnston?], 6 [___] 1799, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. George Johnston, Botetourt County, to father, Zachariah Johnston, 16 January 1799, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. William McKee, Lincoln County, to Capt. Zachariah Johnston, Rockbridge County, 25 January 1799, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. William Renick, Lexington, to [___], 13 February 1799, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Samuel KcKee, With [Wythe] Courthouse, to Zachriah (sic) Johnston, Rockbridge County, 1 April 1799, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Joseph Reid, Timber Ridge, to George Johnston, 8 April 1799, 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. George Johnston, Botetourt County, to brother, [___], 23 April [17]99, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Account. Zachariah Johnson (sic), with James Gold, 25 April 1799, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. John Johnston, Staunton, to brother, G[eorge] Johnston,24 May 1799, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston to father, Zachariah Johnston, 5 June [17]99, 1 p. (1 print)
- Account. Estate of Zachariah Johnston, deceased, to the estate of George Johnston, 1800, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. George Johnston, Flat Country, to brother, Thomas Johnston, 19 March 1800, 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. George Johnston, Lexington, to brother, Thomas Johnston, 10 May 1800, 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. George Johnston, Lexington, to brother, [___], 25 June 1800, 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. George Johnston, Lexington, to brother, [___], 24 July 1800, 2 p.(2 prints)
- Letter. George Johnston, Lexington, to brother, Thomas Johnston, 27 July 1800, 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Rebeckah Dunlap, [Shelby] County, Kentucky, to sister, Mrs. Ann Jonson (sic), 11 September 1800, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Samuel McKee, Staunton, to George Johnston, near Lexington, 31 September 1800, 2 p. (3 prints)
- Land Grant. 51 acres in Rockbridge County to Isaac Anderson, by James Monroe, Governor of Virginia, recorded 20 March 1801, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston, Staunton, to mother and sisters, 21 August 1801, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. John Johnston, Brownsburg, to Thomas [___], 29 August 1801, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. John Johnston, Staunton, to brother, [___], [1]2 September 1801, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Elisabeth Shanklin to sister, Ann Johnston, near Lexington, 1[?] February 1802, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston, Bell [___], to brother, 24[?] February 1802[?], 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston, Staunton, to Thomas Johnston, 13 April 1804, 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. John Johnston, Staunton, to Thomas Johnston, 10 October 1804, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston, Staunton, to brother, Thomas Johnston, 1 March 1805?, 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. Sally Winant, Lincoln County, to Thomas Johnston, Lexington, 8 August 1808, 2 p. (3 prints)
- Account. Rosanah Ervine with [___], 16 September 1812, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Jean Sharp, Seveir (sic) County, to mother, Mrs. Ann Johnston, 21 July 1816 [1 p. (1 print)]; Enclosure is letter from Jean Sharp to Mrs. Ann Johnston [2 p. (2 prints)]
- Letter. John and Jean Sharp, Sevier County, to Mrs. Ann Johnston, 23 February 1817, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Sharp to Thomas Johnston, 27 July 1817, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Jean Sharp, Sevier County, to mother, Mrs. Ann Johnston, 1 March 1818, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Will. Ann Johnston, dated 12 June 1818, 1 p. (1 print), copy
- Account. Sale of property of Ann Johnston deceased, at public sale, 30 September 1818, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John and Jean Sharp, Seveer (sic) County, to Thomas Johnston, 22 November 1819, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Promissory note. Alexander Johnson to Caruthers & Cummings, 4 February 1822, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Sharp, Sevier County, Tennessee, to Thomas Jonston (sic), 21 December 1828, 2 p. (2 prints)
- Notice. Mr. Johnston to pay Mr. T. Perry the money due Elizabeth Wallace, [___] December 1836, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John P. Caruthers, Holly Springs, to Thomas Johnston, near Lexington, 4? September 1837, 2 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. [___], Cumberland County, Kentucky, to cousin, Mrs. [___] Johnston, Rockbridge County, 27 September 1839?, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Bond. William Johnston to James Johnson, both parties of Rockbridge County, 30 April 1840, 2 p. (4 prints)
- Promissory note. William G. Johnston and Zach Johnston to James Johnston, 31 January 1846, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Promissory note. James Johnston to William G. Johnston, 12 June 1848, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Promissory note. James Johnston to William G. Johnston, 12 June 1848, 1 p. (1 print)
- Promissory note. James Johnston to William G. Johnston, 12 June 1848, 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Mary A. M. Robinson, Randolph County, Missouri, to sister, Barbara [___], 29 January 1856, 4 p. (4 prints)
- Letter. John Johnston to Thomas [Johnston?], n.d., 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. John Johnston to Thomas [Johnston?], n.d., 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. Esther Johnston to father and mother, n.d., 1 p. (1 print)
- Letter. A. Johnston to brother, Thomas John[ston],n.d., 3 p. (3 prints)
- Letter. J[ohn] Marshall to Zachariah Johnston, Rockbridge County, n.d., 1 p. (2 prints), incomplete
- Letter. J[ohn] Marshall to Zachariah Johnston, n.d., 1 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. Zachariah Johnston to [___], n.d., 1 p. (1 print), incomplete
- Notes. John Shaw to [___], n.d., 2 p. (2 prints)
- Plat. Land included in "the fork Survey & old patent of Galloway", n.d., 1 p. (2 prints)
- Plat. Land included in the "fork survey", n.d., 1 p. (2 prints)
- Arbitrators' report. Settlement of differences between Rosanah Irvin and Joseph Allen, n.d., 1 p. (1 prints)
- Appraisal. List of property of Mrs. Ann Johnson (sic), deceased, n.d., 1 p. (1 print)
- Poem by unidentified author, n.d., 2 p. (2 prints)
- "A List of Expences to Richmond", n.d., 1 p. (1 print)
- Notice. Zachariah Johnston to [___], n.d., 2 p. (2 prints)
- Letter. John Culbreath to [___], n.d., 1 p. (1 print)
- Biography. "Zachariah Johnston of Augusta and Rockbridge and His Times", n.d., Booklet, 26 p. (26 prints), typescript)